Rudolph Schaeffer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Photographs, 1880s-circa 1988, Series 10:; (Boxes 8-10, 15, OV 18; 1.3 linear ft.)
  - Artwork, circa 1907-1980, 10.1:
    - Exhibition Installations (Box 8)
      - Unidentified Exhibition(s) (featuring flower arrangements), undated (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Flower Arrangements, 1931-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Models for Student Interior Design Projects, undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Paintings, undated (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Schaeffer, Rudolph (Box 8)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 8, Folder 38)
      - Stage Designs (see 10.5: Stage Designs) (Box 8)
      - Wall Decorations, undated (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Screens, undated (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Sculpture, undated (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - People, 1880s-1980s, 10.2:
    People portrayed here are mainly Rudolph Schaeffer, the Schaeffer family, friends and students. Of particular note are a photograph of Frank Lloyd Wright’s visit to the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, and a photograph of Rudolph Schaeffer with Imogen Cunningham.
    - Rudolph Schaeffer, 1880s-1980s, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 42-45)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Chang-Dai-Chien, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Classmates, 1899-1904 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Family (?), circa 1900-1930 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Frank Lloyd Wright and Students, 1958 or 1959 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Imogen Cunningham, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer with Others, 1913-1914, 1960s-1980s, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 51-53)
    - Family, Parents (Julius and Mary Hirzel Schaeffer), undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 1)
    - Others, Individuals and Groups, 1932-1984, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 2)
  - Places, circa 1907-1983, 10.3:
    Places include interior and exterior views of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design at its St. Anne Street and Mariposa Street locations, travel pictures of Laguna Beach and Mt. Wilson, and unidentified buildings and landscapes.
    - Buildings, Unidentified, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 3)
    - Columbus, Ohio, Manual, Training School, circa 1907 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 4)
    - Home of Cousin Karl (?) Schaeffer (interior view), undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 5)
    - Laguna Beach, circa 1913 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 6)
    - Landscapes, Unidentified (Box 9 (hol), Folder 7)
    - Mt. Wilson, 1910 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 8)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design (Box 9 (hol))
      - Mariposa Street, 1970-1981, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 9)
      - St. Anne Street, undated, (see also: OV 18) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 10)
    - Summer Cabin, Dos Rios, Calif., 1983, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 11)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, St. Anne Street, undated (Box OV 18)
  - Events, 1937-1976, 10.4:
    Among the events depicted are an arts festival, an exhibition opening, a graduation and parties held at the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. Stage sets photographed were designed by Rudolph Schaeffer for productions in San Francisco and Detroit. Among the miscellaneous subjects are horses, Rudolph Schaeffer’s collection of Asian art and his headstone in Clare, Michigan.
    - Arts Festival, Aquatic Park, 1954 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 12)
    - Exhibition Opening, "Selections from the Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Oriental Art," Asian Art Museum of San Francisco, 1976 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 13)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design Graduation, 1971 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 14)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design Parties, 1937-1962 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Stage Designs, circa 1920s, 10.5:
    - Detroit ("Pelleas and Melisande," "A Midsummer Night’s Dream"), 1921 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 16)
    - San Francisco (Box 9 (hol))
      - Children’s Theatre of San Francisco (unidentified), 1922 or 1923, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 17)
      - Civic Auditorium ("Fantasy in Snowland"), 1922 or 1923 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 18)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 19)
    - Seattle (The Cornish School?, unidentified), 1920s (Box 9 (hol), Folder 20)
    - Unknown Location(s) (Box 9 (hol))
      - A-Z by Title, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 21-22)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects, circa 1910-circa 1988, 10.6:
    - Automobile, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 24)
    - Christmas Ornaments, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 25)
    - Horses, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 26)
    - Rudolph Schaeffer Collection (Asian art), 1986, undated (Box 9 (hol), Folder 27)
    - Schaeffer Headstone (Clare, Mich.), circa 1988 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 28)
  - Photograph Album, undated, 10.7:
    A photograph album contains views of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design on St. Anne Street, exhibition installations, selections from Rudolph Schaeffer’s collection of Asian art, and student work.
    - Photograph Album, undated, (1 vol., disbound) (Box 10 (pam), Folder 1)
  - Negatives, Slides, and Color Transparencies, circa 1958-circa 1969, 10.8:
    - Artwork (Box 10 (pam))
      - Exhibition Installations (Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Rocks, Kansas City), circa 1969 (Box 10 (pam), Folder 2)
      - Flower Arrangements, undated (Box 10 (pam), Folder 3)
      - "Modern Art Pots for Flowers, Rudolph F. Schaeffer Crafts and Art Studio, Piedmont," 1910s (Box 10 (pam), Folder 4)
    - People (Box 10 (pam))
      - Rudolph Schaeffer (painting; planting a tree), undated (Box 10 (pam), Folder 5)
      - Rudolph Schaeffer with Others (Frank Lloyd Wright and Students; unidentified), 1958 or 1959, undated (Box 10 (pam), Folder 6)
    - Places, Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design (Mariposa Street), undated (Box 10 (pam), Folder 7)
- Unprocessed Accretion, circa 1908-1986, Series 11:; (Boxes 19-20; 1.3 linear ft.)
  An additional 1.3 linear feet of papers was accessioned in 2007 and remains mostly unprocessed. The material in this accretion dates from circa 1908-1986 and contains printed materials, including those relating to the Rudolf Schaeffer School of Design; artwork, including small paintings done by students of the school, and hand-batiked fabric samples from the Weiner Verkstatte; photographs of Schaeffer and friends, Schaeffer's collection of art work, three photographs by Ansel Adams of the home of Fred and Caroline Frey, and several hand-crafted photograph albums; a 1982 oral history interview with Schaeffer; a 1974 manuscript by Schaeffer entitled, "Rythmo-Chromatic Design and the Creative Process" and Volume 1 of an unfinished folio of flower arrangements by Schaeffer; published books by others; one letter to Scaeffer's mother; and other scattered materials.
  These papers have been minimally arranged.
  - Books by Others Deutche Werkkunst, 1916 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Books by Others, circa 1980s (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Album, "Rudolph Schaeffer Remembered", circa 1980s (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Schaeffer and Others, circa 1915-1980s (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Photograph Album of Schaeffer's Summer Garden, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Three Photographs by Ansel Adams of the Home of Fred and Caroline Frey, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Schaeffer's Mother, 1908 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Printed Materials, circa 1916-1949 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Oral History Interview Transcript, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Writings by Scaeffer (includes folio on flower arranging and "Rythmo-Chromatic Design and the Creative Process"), circa 1970s - circa 1980s (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Student Thesis, 1949, 1950 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Student Artwork, circa 1920s (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Matted Hand-Batiked Weiner Verkstatte (Vienna Workshops) Fabric Samples (includes samples by Josef Hoffman and Kolom Moser), circa 1920s, (6 folders) (Box 19, Folder 13-18)
  - Oversized Matted Hand-Batiked Weiner Verkstatte (Vienna Workshops) Fabric Sample, circa 1920s (Box 20 (sol), Folder 1)
  - Handmade Photograph Album by Gail Reynolds Natzler (includes photos of her work and of Scaeffer), 1980 (Box 20 (sol), Folder 2)
  - Oversized Photograph of actress Peggy Cuddy, an acquaintance of Schaeffer's, circa 1920s - 1930s (Box 20 (sol), Folder 3)